<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BrainVascular.com</title>
    <link>https://devcows.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on BrainVascular.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://devcows.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Aneurysm</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/aneurysms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/aneurysms/</guid>
      <description>On this page you will find information about brain aneurysms and their treatment.
 Introduction to brain aneurysms Diagnosis of brain aneurysms Signs and symptoms of brain aneurysms Treatment of ruptured aneurysms Treatment of unruptured aneurysms Additional resources  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arteriovenous malformations</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/avm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/avm/</guid>
      <description>On this page you will find information about arteriovenous malformations and their treatment.
 Introduction to arteriovenous malformations Signs and symptoms Diagnosis Treatment  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/contact/</guid>
      <description>We are here to help you </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DAVF treatment</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/davf/treatment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/davf/treatment/</guid>
      <description>How can endovascular treatment help? “Endovascular” means that access to the brain or surroundings is achieved by threading a very fine tube through your arteries. Embolisation is a way of blocking abnormal blood vessels and is usually carried out to prevent the DAVF from bleeding. This is done by injecting a special glue-like liquid into the DAVF to cut off the blood vessels supplying the fistula.
Endovascular treatment is performed by specialist doctors called interventional neuroradiologists (INRs)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/aneurysms/diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/aneurysms/diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>When it comes to diagnosing brain aneurysms, a range of imaging technologies may be used. Here is an overview of these different modalities:
Computerised Tomography (CT Scan) A CT scan employs X-rays to create a detailed image of the brain. This technology is widely available, quick, and particularly effective in identifying bleeding in or around the brain, which can occur if an aneurysm ruptures. The scan may be performed with or without a &amp;lsquo;contrast&amp;rsquo; dye, which helps in distinguishing different brain structures more clearly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/avm/diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/avm/diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>There are three primary imaging techniques used in the diagnosis and investigation of brain AVMs: computed tomography (CT), magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), and cerebral angiography.
Computed Tomography (CT)
A CT scan is usually the initial imaging study performed when a patient is symptomatic. A CT scan is a type of X-ray that produces detailed cross-sectional images of the brain. It can suggest the approximate site of a bleed if one has occurred.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/davf/diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/davf/diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>Diagnosing a Dural arteriovenous fistula (DAVF) involves a series of tests and procedures to confirm the presence of a DAVF and to understand its size, location, and the exact pattern of abnormal blood flow.
Medical History and Physical Examination Your doctor will first take a detailed medical history, ask you about your symptoms, and perform a physical examination. They might also ask about any history of trauma, infection, or surgery, as these can sometimes be associated with DAVF.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diagnosis</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/spinalvascular/diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/spinalvascular/diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>Spinal vascular malformations can be challenging to diagnose due to their symptoms often mirroring those of other spinal conditions, such as spinal dural arteriovenous fistula, spinal stenosis, multiple sclerosis, or a spinal cord tumor.
To determine the cause of your symptoms, your doctor will likely recommend several tests, including:
  Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI): This imaging test uses strong magnetic fields and radio waves to produce detailed images of your spinal cord.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diagnosis of stroke</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/stroke/diagnosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/stroke/diagnosis/</guid>
      <description>Diagnosing a stroke involves the use of imaging technologies to view the brain and detect any abnormalities. Let&amp;rsquo;s delve into the details of how doctors diagnose a stroke.
Radiology scans are the primary diagnostic tools for identifying stroke. They help distinguish between ischaemic stroke (caused by a blockage) and haemorrhagic stroke (caused by bleeding).
Computed Tomography (CT) Scan A CT scan of the brain is often the first imaging modality used in suspected stroke cases because it is quick, affordable, and widely available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dural arteriovenous fistula</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/davf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/davf/</guid>
      <description>On this page you will find information about cranial dural arteriovenous fistulas and their treatment.
 Introduction to dural arteriovenous fistulas Signs and symptoms Diagnosis Treatment  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Further resources</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/aneurysms/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/aneurysms/links/</guid>
      <description>United Kingdom  The Brain &amp;amp; Spine Foundation: The Brain &amp;amp; Spine Foundation provides professional information and support for neurological conditions affecting those living in the UK.  United States  The Aneurysm and AVM Foundation: This based charity is dedicated to bettering the lives, support networks, and medical care of those affected by aneurysm and other types of vascular malformation of the brain.    National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke: A service of the National Institutes of Health.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Further resources</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/stroke/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/stroke/links/</guid>
      <description>United Kingdom  Different Strokes: Different Strokes is a UK based stroke charity run by younger stroke survivors for younger stroke survivors.   National Stroke Association: Provides resources on stroke prevention, treatment, and recovery, as well as resources for healthcare professionals and stroke survivors.   The Brain &amp;amp; Spine Foundation: The Brain &amp;amp; Spine Foundation provides professional information and support for neurological conditions affecting those living in the UK.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/davf/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/davf/introduction/</guid>
      <description>What is a dural arteriovenous fistula? A dural arteriovenous fistula (DAVF) is an abnormal connection between the arteries and veins of the brain.
Normally a fine network of microscopic capillaries connects arteries and veins in all tissues including the brain. Capillaries assist in slowing down the blood flow between arteries and veins. A DAVF is a tangle of feeding arteries and draining veins in the brain that have abnormal connections which bypass the normal capillaries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction of spinal vascular malformations</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/spinalvascular/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/spinalvascular/introduction/</guid>
      <description>Spinal vascular malformations are uncommon conditions that involve abnormal connections between blood vessels in your spinal cord. They are essential to recognize because, if left undiagnosed and untreated, they can lead to serious complications. Symptoms can vary from person to person and can include pain, numbness, weakness, or difficulty moving your limbs. Bladder and bowel function can be impaired. The process of diagnosing these conditions is frequently prolonged due to the gradual onset of symptoms and limited awareness of the disease among non-expert practitioners.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to brain aneurysms</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/aneurysms/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/aneurysms/introduction/</guid>
      <description>What is an aneurysm? An aneurysm is a bulge in the wall of a blood vessel caused by a small area of weakness. Aneurysms can occur in various parts of the body, but one of the most common locations is the brain. These are known as intracranial or cerebral aneurysms. This bulge can lead to the rupture of the aneurysm, resulting in severe bleeding around the brain called subarachnoid haemorrhage.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to brain arteriovenous malformations</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/avm/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/avm/introduction/</guid>
      <description>A brain arteriovenous malformation (AVM) is a complex, abnormal network of blood vessels in the brain. In a healthy brain, blood circulates from arteries to veins via tiny vessels called capillaries. The capillaries allow for the exchange of oxygen and nutrients from the blood to the brain tissue, and the removal of waste products. However, in a brain AVM, direct connections form between the arteries and veins, bypassing these capillaries. This abnormality can disrupt normal blood flow and oxygen circulation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to stroke</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/stroke/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/stroke/introduction/</guid>
      <description>What is a Stroke? A stroke is a medical emergency caused by a sudden interruption in the blood flow to the brain, leading to cell death due to lack of oxygen. This is often due to a blood clot blocking a vessel (ischaemic stroke) or bleeding in or around the brain (hemorrhagic stroke). When oxygen supply is cut off, neurological functions become impaired, manifesting in a variety of symptoms.
Types of Stroke There are two major categories of strokes:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our editorial policy</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/editorial-policy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/editorial-policy/</guid>
      <description>We are dedicated to delivering reliable, precise, and current health information to both the general public and healthcare professionals worldwide. All the health information available on our platform are completely independent of any commercial interests or influences. Our content is based on trustworthy research evidence, established UK, US, and European medical guidelines, and the highest standards of clinical practice. We adhere to UK spelling and terminology in our editorial approach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Patient resources</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/links/</guid>
      <description>United Kingdom  Different Strokes: Different Strokes is a UK based stroke charity run by younger stroke survivors for younger stroke survivors.   National Stroke Association: Provides resources on stroke prevention, treatment, and recovery, as well as resources for healthcare professionals and stroke survivors.   The Brain &amp;amp; Spine Foundation: The Brain &amp;amp; Spine Foundation provides professional information and support for neurological conditions affecting those living in the UK.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ruptured aneurysms</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/aneurysms/ruptured-aneurysms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/aneurysms/ruptured-aneurysms/</guid>
      <description>What are the consequences of aneurysm rupture? Aneurysm rupture results in a severe headache caused by bleeding around the brain, termed subarachnoid haemorrhage. A common description of this is a &amp;ldquo;thunderclap&amp;rdquo; headache. It may be accompanied by a stiff neck, sickness, vomiting, sensitivity to light, and loss of consciousness. Aneurysmal haemorrhage may lead to death. Rates of death vary in different studies and range from 20-50% [1]. It is likely that the death rate from aneurysm rupture is decreasing over time due to advances in medical care.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Signs and symptoms</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/spinalvascular/symptoms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/spinalvascular/symptoms/</guid>
      <description>The symptoms of spinal vascular malformations can widely vary from person to person. They are largely dependent on the location and severity of the malformation. Some individuals may not experience noticeable symptoms for many years, or even at all, while others may endure symptoms that severely disrupt daily activities or present life-threatening risks.
These conditions typically present symptoms during early adulthood, but it&amp;rsquo;s worth noting that a significant percentage of those diagnosed are under the age of 16.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Signs and symptoms of arteriovenous malformations</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/avm/symptoms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/avm/symptoms/</guid>
      <description>Brain and spine arteriovenous malformations (AVMs) are abnormal tangles of blood vessels consisting of connections between the arteries and veins. They often do not cause any clinical problems until they rupture. AVMs can cause symptoms either by bleeding (rupturing), pressing on the brain or spinal cord, or by reducing the amount of oxygen reaching the brain tissue.
Symptoms might include the following:
Bleeding Brain AVMs may cause bleeding into the brain (haemorrhage), causing sudden, severe headaches, confusion, nausea, vomiting, and may lead to a loss of consciousness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Signs and symptoms of brain aneurysms</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/aneurysms/symptoms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/aneurysms/symptoms/</guid>
      <description>A brain aneurysm typically doesn&amp;rsquo;t present symptoms until it&amp;rsquo;s large or ruptures. However, it&amp;rsquo;s crucial to recognise potential signs to seek timely medical help.
Ruptured Brain Aneurysm A ruptured aneurysm is a medical emergency. Symptoms may include:
 Sudden, severe headache (&amp;ldquo;worst headache of your life&amp;rdquo;) Neck stiffness or pain Light sensitivity (photophobia) Sudden blurred or double vision Sudden pain above or behind the eye Changes in mental status or awareness Difficulty walking or sudden dizziness Sudden weakness and numbness  Most of the time aneurysm rupture is a serious and dramatic event that would be very noticeable to the patient.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Signs and symptoms of dural arteriovenous fistula</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/davf/symptoms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/davf/symptoms/</guid>
      <description>A Dural Arteriovenous Fistula (DAVF) is an abnormal connection between an artery and a vein in the tough covering over the brain or spine (the dura). It is a rare, but serious condition.
Not everyone with a Dural Arteriovenous Fistula will experience symptoms, and symptoms can vary based on the location and characteristics of the DAVF. The symptoms may develop gradually and subtly or can become suddenly apparent. If you experience any of these symptoms, especially the severe ones, it&amp;rsquo;s important to seek immediate medical help.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Signs and symptoms of stroke</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/stroke/symptoms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/stroke/symptoms/</guid>
      <description>Recognizing the Symptoms of a Stroke A stroke can be a life-threatening condition, and it&amp;rsquo;s crucial to recognise the signs and act quickly to get medical help. If you suspect that you or someone else is experiencing a stroke, it&amp;rsquo;s essential to seek medical help immediately. Rapid action can significantly improve outcomes and reduce the long-term effects of a stroke. Remember, every minute counts.
1. Understanding Stroke Symptoms A stroke can cause a range of symptoms, depending on which part of the brain is affected.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spinal vascular malformations</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/spinalvascular/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/spinalvascular/</guid>
      <description>On this page you will find information about spinal vascular malformations and their treatment.
 Introduction to spinal vascular malformations Signs and symptoms Diagnosis Treatment  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stroke</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/stroke/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/stroke/</guid>
      <description>On this page you will find information about stroke and its treatment.
 Introduction Signs and symptoms  Diagnosis Treatment Additional resources  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Treatment</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/spinalvascular/treatment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/spinalvascular/treatment/</guid>
      <description>Treating spinal vascular malformations typically involves a combination of methods aimed at alleviating symptoms and minimizing the risk of potential complications. The treatment plan is customized based on various factors such as the size, location, and blood flow of the malformation, your neurological exam findings, and your overall health status.
The primary aim of treating spinal vascular malformations is to mitigate the risk of bleeding and halt or prevent the progression of disability and other symptoms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Treatment</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/stroke/treatment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/stroke/treatment/</guid>
      <description>Stroke treatment involves immediate interventions like thrombolysis and thrombectomy, neurosurgical procedures, and supportive care, followed by long-term risk factor management. This article delves into these strategies, outlining their significance in stroke recovery and future stroke prevention.
Thrombolysis Thrombolysis, a procedure involving the dissolution of blood clots, plays a crucial role in the treatment of acute ischemic stroke. It is especially effective when administered within the first three hours of symptom onset.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Treatment of brain AVMs</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/avm/treatment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/avm/treatment/</guid>
      <description>The treatment of brain arteriovenous malformations (AVMs) depends on several factors, including the AVM&amp;rsquo;s location and size, and whether it has caused bleeding.
Medical Treatment
Anticonvulsant medications, such as phenytoin, are used to control seizures. Other medications or procedures can be employed to relieve pressure inside the skull caused by the AVM. Curative treatment may be required eventually to prevent hemorrhage. However, all interventions come with some risk of causing neurological deficits.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unruptured aneurysm</title>
      <link>https://devcows.github.io/topics/aneurysms/unruptured-aneurysms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devcows.github.io/topics/aneurysms/unruptured-aneurysms/</guid>
      <description>I have an aneurysm. Does it need to be treated? Not necessarily. Aneurysms can be dangerous but some require no treatment at all. The decision to treat is often a complex one and requires discussion with an experienced medical professional. Any medical treatment involves a degree of risk, no matter how small. It is probable that for certain low-risk aneurysms the risk of the aneurysm is outweighed by the risk of the treatment.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
